<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Railslide - linux</title><link href="https://railslide.io/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://railslide.io/feeds/linux.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://railslide.io/</id><updated>2022-04-07T00:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>How to resolve screen flickering in Arch</title><link href="https://railslide.io/how-to-resolve-screen-flickering-in-arch.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2022-04-07T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-04-07T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Giulia</name></author><id>tag:railslide.io,2022-04-07:/how-to-resolve-screen-flickering-in-arch.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;How to solve screen flickering in Arch when using Intel graphics and systemd-boot&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After a system upgrade, I got this annoying screen flickering happening at random intervals. Initially I thought the issue was Gnome related, but after a bit of research it turned out to be caused by a &lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Intel_graphics#Screen_flickering"&gt;power saving feature on my Intel graphic card&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution to it is to disable the feature through a kernel parameter. For doing so you need to edit a configuration file specific to the chosen boot loader. In my case it's systemd-boot, so the file was located in &lt;code&gt;/boot/loader/entries/[SOMETHING].conf&lt;/code&gt; (in my case the filename was the timestamp of my system installation, but mileage may vary).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open the file with your favourite editor&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sudo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;nano&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;boot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;loader&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;entries&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;SOMETHING&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;conf&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add &lt;code&gt;i915.enable_psr=0&lt;/code&gt; at the end of the &lt;code&gt;options&lt;/code&gt; line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reboot, and enjoy your epilepsy-free screen time again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Further readings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Intel_graphics"&gt;Arch wiki page about Intel graphics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Kernel_parameters"&gt;Arch wiki page about kernel paremeters&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="linux"/><category term="linux"/><category term="arch"/><category term="intel"/><category term="systemd-boot"/><category term="troubleshooting"/></entry><entry><title>Oh btw, I use Arch</title><link href="https://railslide.io/oh-btw-i-use-arch.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2022-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Giulia</name></author><id>tag:railslide.io,2022-01-31:/oh-btw-i-use-arch.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Somehow I ended up on Arch and so far I'm liking it.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was happily running Manjaro when my computer started to crash multiple times per day. I tried debugging but that did not lead anywhere (it will later turn out to be a hardware issue). So, out of ideas I decided to see if the problem was Manjaro specific and if another distro would solve. And it was at that point that a friend somehow convinced me to give Arch a shot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My approach to Arch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main reason why I've never considered Arch before it was probably that I had the misfortune to run into some terrible Arch users in the past. You know, the &lt;em&gt;Ubuntu is for noobs, installing and running Arch is so complicated, I made it and hence I'm better than you&lt;/em&gt; kind of people. So in my mind Arch was pretty much an elitist overcomplicated distro and I didn't really see any good reason for giving it a shot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What changed my mind then? Well, it has been a combination of things. On one hand - thanks to Manjaro - I got exposed to AUR (Arch User Repository) and grew fond of it. Then on April 1st Arch had released an installer (fun fact: due to the date many thought it was an April's fool) removing the need to install Arch from scratch. Plus, I was extremely frustrated by the frequent crashes and if Arch was the solution so be it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand I realized that a bunch of awesome people in my life were in fact using Arch (I probably had run into nice Arch users even before, but since they didn't go around boosting how cool they were for using Arch I had probably missed that). Plus a part of me secretly regarded Arch as a sort of mandatory step/rite of passage in my linux journey, so when a friend suggested to give Arch a shot I just assumed that the time for it had come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I must say, however, that even though I had bought in to the idea of installing Arch, my expectation was very much of giving it try, finding it too complicated/elitist, and moving to another distro. It turned out that I was very wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Installing Arch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the shiny new installer, the process of installing Arch was generally straightforward. The only part I didn't find very intuitive was accessing the wifi from TTY. Thankfully a friend had provided me with instructions, so that went smoothly as well. For the sake of my future self, here they are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;iwctl&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nv"&gt;stations&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;list&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nv"&gt;stations&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;probably&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;wlan0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;but&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;whatever&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;listed&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;connect&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;SSID&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest went through without too much hassle. A good idea was however to have another computer or a phone ready at hand, for those few times where I felt the need to google something during the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My first steps into the Arch world&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first impression of Arch was that it was very... bare. Being used to distros with a bespoken desktop environment, I was a bit caught off guard when I first logged in. I had picked Gnome during the installation and what I got was indeed Gnome, just stripped to the bare minimum - anything else I wanted I had to install it myself. Don't get me wrong though, that's a good thing! Yes, I did have to figure out what was the name of the components I wanted and how to install them, but after a bit of fiddling I got my DE to work, look and feel exactly the way I wanted. And if that's not the beauty of linux in a nutshell, I don't what that is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing I noticed is the speed of my system. Compared to a fresh installation of Ubuntu, Arch is just blazing fast. I guess that's probably one of the perks on of not having a lot of useless software installed from the start. Again, yes, I had to install everything I need out of the box, but that also means my system resources are spent only on programs I actually use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, I cannot really stress enough what an amazing documentation and community Arch has. The internet is full of people praising the Arch wiki and I totally agree - for 99% of the issues I encountered the solution was documented there. And the remaining 1% was usually covered by the &lt;a href="https://bbs.archlinux.org/"&gt;Arch Linux Forum on BBS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Package management&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I mentioned to people that I was considering Arch (the fist step of installing Arch is to tell everyone that you're installing Arch :D), I got many warnings around package management. They mostly boiled down to two topics: rolling releases and Aur packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main critique with rolling releases is that you need to monitor which packages you're installing, since you might end up with something &lt;em&gt;too new&lt;/em&gt; to play nice with the rest of them. My experience with it is that, while I do pay a bit more attention when critical packages show up in the list (e.g. new kernel, or Gnome related stuff), I've yet to end up in such a scenario. Maybe I'm just lucky, but so far these 8 months have been smooth from that perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with AUR packages my experience has been just positive. It probably helps that I'm comfortable with reading code, but having to check the PKGBUILD file before installing a package is not that big of a hassle for me. And I really love the concept of a community-driven package repository! Plus now that thanks to Yay (if you don't use it, have a look at it - it's awesome!) I can handle both AUR and Arch packages from the same place, I'm an even happier camper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, I'm very happy with Arch. While it probably isn't the perfect distro for everyone (is there such a thing?), it certainly turned out to be a great fit for me.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="linux"/><category term="os"/><category term="linux"/><category term="distro"/><category term="arch"/></entry><entry><title>Switching from Ubuntu to Manjaro</title><link href="https://railslide.io/switching-from-ubuntu-to-manjaro.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-12-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-12-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Giulia</name></author><id>tag:railslide.io,2021-12-26:/switching-from-ubuntu-to-manjaro.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After many years on Ubuntu I decided it was time for some distro hopping and I gave Manjaro a spin.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been an Ubuntu user for about 14 years and while I have been using other distros (mostly on servers) from time to time, I never felt the need to switch away from it. Lately though a mix of curiosity and some Ubuntu stuff rubbing my nerves gave me the nudge to try something else. I had heard good things about Manjaro, so I decided to give it a shot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What's wrong with Ubuntu?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's be clear, I don't hate Ubuntu. I still believe it's a great distro and definitely a great candidate for beginner and experienced users alike. That said, there were some things that annoyed me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the top of the list of my pain points there were Snap packages. When they were announced I thought it was a great idea. Containerized, cross-distribution applications - what's not to like? But while theory was great, practice turned out to be fairly mediocre: snap packages are slow, they clutter the filesystem, and they don't always work with your system theme. AppImage and Flatpak are way better alternatives and I would take them over Snap every given day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides not being a not-so-great user experience, Snap packages also come with some ethical concerns. Ideally if I don't like them I could just stay away from them, right? Unfortunately that's easier said than done. Since Ubuntu 20.04 installing Chromium via Apt will install Chromium as a Snap package instead of a native one. &lt;a href="https://snapcraft.io/blog/chromium-in-ubuntu-deb-to-snap-transition"&gt;The reason for this change was that the native package required developers to build releases for every supported version Ubuntu, while Snap allows them to maintain a single package that works on all of them&lt;/a&gt;. The problem though is that this switcharoo happens without warning or asking the user. Don't get me wrong, as a developer myself I understand that maintaining Chromium might have been a gigantic pain in the ass, but I also believe that simply printing out a notice rather than go ahead and install a snap package would have gone a long way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a similar note, I was also surprised to discover that Ubuntu Disk Creator doesn't support ISO images for anything other than Ubuntu and its flavours. I am aware that this is old news, but I still found it fairly irritating, since it felt a bit like being punished (&lt;em&gt;no GUI for you!&lt;/em&gt;) for going for a different distro. Also, the fact that the official Ubuntu guide suggested two ppa as alternatives was not super encouraging either. And while this wasn't a deal breaker per se, it added up to my frustration. So, when the opportunity came along in the form of a new work laptop, I decided it was time to explore the distro landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Enter Manjaro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manjaro is a user-friendly distro based on Arch, which means rolling releases and access to the Arch User Repository (AUR). It also comes with its own dedicated software repositories, a graphical installer, automatic hardware detection, and pre-installed codecs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The good parts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being based on Arch, Manjaro is fast and has a low memory footprint. Installation goes in a breeze (around 2 minutes!) and I was surprised on how little it took me to have it up and running. I later installed Ubuntu on the same machine and it felt like waiting for ages in comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next thing I really appreciated with Manjaro is that it gives the user a lot of freedom when it comes to customization. Take the desktop environment for example: the Manjaro development team provides and maintains XFCE, KDE and Gnome editions out of the box. On top of that, the community maintains 6 additional flavours (i3, Budgie, Cinnamon, Deepin, Mate, and Sway). So, whatever is favourite DE, you're likely to get it covered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another awesome feature is that Manjaro natively supports Flatpak, Snap, and Aur packages. Whatever you want to use it's up to you, all it takes is toggling a setting in the package manager. No more surprise Snap packages popping up in your system - if you want to use Snap you do, if you don't you don't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also loved the extensive community support. Besides the already mentioned community editions, Manjaro also has an extensive an lively forum where users can get help from other community members. This reminded me of Ask Ubuntu (definitely one of Ubuntu's strengths in my opinion!) and I was very pleased to see that Manjaro had something similar - in 99% of the cases I stumbled on some issue or had doubts, a quick search on there provided me with all the answers I needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, Manjaro looks good. While aesthetic is not my primary concern when it comes to choosing an operative system, I must admit that I always found Ubuntu's default appearance somehow outdated and not very appealing. Again, not a breaking deal per se, but it was refreshing to work on something that pleased the eye without any further action on my side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The bad parts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While in general I really liked Manjaro, it would be a lie to say that it is free from flaws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My major complain about it are its disk encryption settings. By default if you decide to encrypt your disk, Manjaro will encrypt everything including the boot partition. The good part is that an encrypted boot partition comes with the perk of not being vulnerable to an &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evil_maid_attack"&gt;evil maid attack&lt;/a&gt;. Though the bad part is that it comes with several drawbacks on your day-to-day activities, such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decryption is slow because it cannot leverage hardware acceleration and it can takes up to 20/30 seconds. So booting your computer takes time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You only have one try to type the decryption key correctly. If you make a typo, you'll have to reboot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The correct keyboard layout is not loaded yet, so if you're using special chars good luck with that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A workaround for it is to do a manual partitioning and leave &lt;code&gt;/boot&lt;/code&gt; unencrypted. However documentation and/or steps-by-steps instructions for how to do it are not easy to find, and even if you know how to do it you might still bump into some &lt;a href="https://github.com/calamares/calamares/issues/1073"&gt;installer bug&lt;/a&gt; and end up with an unbootable system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general I got a really nice impression of Manjaro and I definitely landed in my list of recommended distros.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will I stay with it? Well, I ended up not to. Due to frequent crashes to my machine, I tried to install other distros to see if it was something related to Manjaro. While the problem turned out to be a hardware issue, the debugging process resulted in me stumbling on the above Calamares bug when trying to go back to Manjaro, getting frustrated, and eventually install something else (more on this in another post!). That said, I'd be more than willing to give Manjaro another chance in the future, once such bug gets fixed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TL;DR: a great distro, with some encryption pain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="linux"/><category term="os"/><category term="linux"/><category term="distro"/><category term="manjaro"/><category term="ubuntu"/></entry></feed>