<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Railslide</title><link href="http://railslide.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://railslide.io/feeds/utilities.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://railslide.io/</id><updated>2014-09-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Hello Vagrant! (aka development environment made easy)</title><link href="http://railslide.io/hello-vagrant.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-09-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Giulia Vergottini</name></author><id>tag:railslide.io,2014-09-14:hello-vagrant.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;For a long time my first step for starting a PHP based project has been to install Xampp on my machine. Xampp provides a considerably easy-to-install full lamp stack - no question about that. However, when I started working on more complicated projects which implied to work together with other developers issues started rising. The main problem was the differences between my local environment and the production one. Add the a further layer of differences for potentially each person involved in the project and it doesn't take much to figure out that moving the result of your work somewhere else than your machine was a guaranteed headache.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now imagine a full LAMP stack that gets activated with a command as simple as &lt;code&gt;vagrant up&lt;/code&gt; and takes automatically care of all the dependencies and needed libraries. Add on top of it that it's easily portable and tailored to your needs and you should already have enough reasons for giving Vagrant a try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are still not fully convinced or just curios, here is a more detailed insight of how Vagrant increases productivity and makes your life so incredibly easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Exactly what you need&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since you are the one provisioning your virtual machine, you get the total freedom of setting it up the way you want. This means that you can have a VM that perfectly replicates your production environment, removing thus all the potentially annoying discrepancies between your local system and the production one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Setup only once&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All you need for bringing up a VM with Vagrant is just the Vagrantfile and the provision script(s). Once you have those you are just a &lt;code&gt;vagrant up&lt;/code&gt; away from that very machine every time you need it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the coolness doesn't stop here! If you commit the Vagrantfile and the provision scripts together with the rest of your projects files (and I don't see any good reason why you shouldn't), any developer checking out the code will be able to run the same VM on her/his computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is particularly useful when working in a team, since &lt;em&gt;one person&lt;/em&gt; set up the VM &lt;em&gt;just once&lt;/em&gt; and a whole team benefits from it. Furthermore, thanks to CVS, if someone needs to install a library for carry out her/his job, s/he simply edits the provision file accordingly and commit it. In this way, everyone will get the needed library installed on the VM and so long forgotten dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Develop the way you like&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vagrant automatically syncs files between the host and the guest machine. So there's no need to change anything in your beloved setup nor to use something other than your favorite editor. Any file you edit locally in a synced folder will automagically appear in the VM as well, ready to be used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Multiple machines? Not a problem!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vagrant allow you to have multiple VMs within the same project. They can communicate to each other, so that you can accurately reproduce the production environment of your multi-servers killer app. By the way, they are also independent from each other, so no need of bringing them all up when you need to work on only one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summing up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess it's pretty obvious that I am a huge fan of Vagrant. It makes my life so much easier (and my working team's too!) and I can no longer imagine my development workflow without it. Finally, the fact that it's also open source it's just the cherry on top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://vagrantup.com/"&gt;Vagrant homepage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="vagrant"></category><category term="virtual machine"></category><category term="development environment"></category></entry><entry><title>Setting up a dotfiles repo and easily port configurations around</title><link href="http://railslide.io/dotfiles.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-07-10T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Giulia Vergottini</name></author><id>tag:railslide.io,2014-07-10:dotfiles.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After having spent quite some time in finding the right set up for my developing environment, it came natural to look for a way for porting my configuration. Enter a dotfiles repo, aka having all my configurations only one &lt;code&gt;git clone&lt;/code&gt; away and making my life so much easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael Smalley wrote an &lt;a href="http://blog.smalleycreative.com/tutorials/using-git-and-github-to-manage-your-dotfiles/"&gt;amazing tutorial&lt;/a&gt; for managing dotfiles and creating a script for automagically installing them (go and check it out!), which provided me with a great starting point. However, his script handles only dotfiles housed in the home directory and that didn't really get together with my goal of adding Sublime Text settings to my dotfiles repo. So I fired up Nano and extended the script in order to make it do exactly what I needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, I needed to to move Sublime configuration files to my dotfiles folder. Thankfully &lt;a href="http://zanshin.net/2013/01/21/sublime-text-2-dotfiles-simplified/"&gt;Mark Nichols' post&lt;/a&gt; tipped me that I the only folder I needed to care about was the User one. So, after cleaning it up from some experiments leftovers, I moved to my dotfiles folder and placed a symlink in its previous location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I added a variable holding the path to the User directory:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;sublimedir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;~/.config/sublime-text-3/Packages/User
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;and at the end of the file the lines taking care of the magic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="c"&gt;# move any existing dotfiles in homedir to dotfiles_old directory, then create symlinks&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;for &lt;/span&gt;file in &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$files&lt;/span&gt;; &lt;span class="k"&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;    if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; -a ~/.&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$file&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;; &lt;span class="k"&gt;then&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class="c"&gt;# check if a dotfile already exists&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nb"&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Moving any existing dotfiles from ~ to $olddir&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
        mv ~/.&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$file&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$olddir&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;fi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Creating symlink to $file in home directory.&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    ln -s &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$dir&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$file&lt;/span&gt; ~/.&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$file&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;done&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nb"&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;...done&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c"&gt;# move Sublime Text Users directory to dotfiles_old directory, then create symlink&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; -d &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$sublimedir&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;; &lt;span class="k"&gt;then&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c"&gt;# check whether the directory already exists&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nb"&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Moving the existing Sublime Text Users directory from $sublimedir to $olddir&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    mv &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$sublimedir&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$olddir&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nb"&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;...done&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;fi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Creating symlink to Users in $sublimedir&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
ln -s &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$dir&lt;/span&gt;/sublime/User &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$sublimedir&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;...done&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The full script can be found on &lt;a href="https://github.com/Railslide/dotfiles/blob/master/installdotfiles.sh"&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, since Package Control updates regularly some of the files in the User folder, I added them to a &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt; file in order to avoid to much noise in my version control. A list of those files can be found in the &lt;a href="https://sublime.wbond.net/docs/syncing"&gt;docs&lt;/a&gt; of Package Control.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="dotfiles"></category><category term="utilities"></category><category term="git"></category></entry></feed>